when we consider the types of things
that will have a sizable impact on our
Health and Longevity there's a no doubt
V2 Max belongs in that conversation
maybe even near the top you may have
heard any number of doctors phds and MDS
espousing V2 as this Holy Grail of
metrics to know how healthy you are and
how long you will live well I'd like to
show you the best way to improve your V2
Max according to a bunch of studies
first off what is V2 Max in short it's
the maximum amount of oxygen that your
body can use during intense physical
activity and why does that matter it
matters because for your body to utilize
oxygen efficiently so many systems have
to be working maximally we're talking
about your diaphragm needing to allow
your lungs to expand your lungs
themselves to have to allow oxygen from
the air into the blood your red blood
cells have to be a to deal with the mass
influx of oxygen that you're sucking
down your lungs your heart has to be
pumping forcefully and fast to move the
red blood cells from the lungs to your
muscles as fast as possible then your
muscles have to take up the oxygen and
have effective mitochondria to generate
cellular energy to propel you through
intense exercise that cellular energy
requires oxygen to be
efficient so like I said multiple
systems with some excluded have to be
working extremely efficiently to
maximize your performance and your
performance won't reach its peak if you
aren't healthy or if one of those
systems is deficient so this one measure
V2 Max is an excellent proxy for health
and performance now many Studies have
looked at V2 to find out what is the
best way to improve it in one analysis
of over 50 studies the researchers
compared all the studies using moderate
intensity cardiovascular exercise
against high intensity exercise so think
long duration running or jogging against
near Sprint or sprinting level of
exercise we can see that data here I'm
not going to bog you down by explaining
everything here but different modalities
of high-intensity training abbreviated
as HIIT or hit here are compared against
moderate intensity exercise we just
mentioned see the 0.0 line there it
indicates no preference one way or
another for v2 Max Improvement however
if the boxes and lines move to the right
it indicates hit improves V2 Max more
than moderate intensity exercise that
still doesn't explain everything going
on here but in general the takeaways
here is that several hit methods were
Superior to moderate intensity exercise
although not all hit methods were better
okay so which ones then
for that we can open up this study where
in the researchers separated people into
four groups to perform four different
intensity exercises across a range of
intensities one group was assigned to do
slow longdistance exercise like the
moderate intensity that we just
described earlier the second group was
told to exercise at a more vigorous
intensity for a shorter amount of time
and the other two groups did variations
of high-intensity training if we look at
the relative effect on V2 Max we have
the slow moderate intensity on the far
left the more vigorous but not high
intensity exercise next to it called LT
and then the two high-intensity training
styles on the right we'll get into the
specifics later for now we can focus on
the white bars because they indicate an
increase in V2 Max across exercise
modalities from a baseline now these
data confirm the previous analysis high
intensity exercise is best for improving
V2 Max so what are these protocols
exactly well before we get into the
specifics of the exercise protocols used
here if you're interested I covered
different features that maximize the
benefits of these protocols as well as
have a more complete step-by-step
protocol from another study and a
step-by-step progression template on how
to improve week to week all of which are
included for the physionic Insiders
assuming that you want more options and
more handholding on designing your
routine than the ones that I'll be going
over now if you do it's linked in the
description ition okay let's cover the
two protocols used in this study one is
called 15x15 interval training
essentially you perform 15 seconds of
sprinting at 90 to 95% of your maximum
heart rate with 15 seconds of active
rest which means that you jog at around
70% of your maximum heart rate you
repeat this 47 times per session the
second protocol is called a 4x4 interval
training it entails 4 minutes of
sprinting at 90 to 95% maximum heart
rate with 3 minutes of active rest again
jogging at 70% of maximum heart rate
this was repeated four times per
session both of these workouts were done
three times per week and if you're
wondering how to find your maximum heart
rate well one easy although imperfect
way is to use this simple formula 220
minus your age the takeaway here is that
the best way to improve V2 is through
high-intensity training and either of
these protocols will work to improve V2
and Supply immense health benefits if
you want more related content check out
this video right here I'll catch you
over there unless you outrun me of
course bye
[Music]